Sara Tinsley Rees Papers, 1875-1929
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Sarah Tinsley Rees Papers
1875-1929
1911-1919
Rees, Sarah Tinsley, 1882-1929
MS 235
6 boxes (2.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Missionary and Red Cross worker. Rees worked as a missionary in Japan and Russia, and as a nurse's aid during World War I. Correspondence includes her many letters from Japan and Siberia, plus letters from her family in the U.S. to Rees. Other materials include memorabilia and photographs.
1882 Born, Macon, GA, October 30
1897 Moved to Hartford, CT
1901 Graduated from Hartford High School
1905 Graduated from Smith College
1911 Graduated from New York Training School for Deaconesses
1911-18 Served as missionary to Japan under the auspices of the Protestant Episcopal Church
1918-19 Served as nurse's aide, Vladivostok, Red Cross Commission to Siberia
1919 Served as nurse's aide aboard Red Cross transport ship
1919-29 Taught English at Hartford High School and served as its first dean and first woman vice principal
1925 Received teacher's certificate
1929 Died July 30
The Sarah Tinsley Rees Papers consist of two linear feet of correspondence (which forms the bulk of the papers), printed material, memorabilia, and photographs. The inclusive dates are 1875 to 1929, but the major portion of the material dates from 1911 to 1919.
The CORRESPONDENCE series consists of three sections: Sarah T. Rees, Family, and Miscellaneous. The first section contains outgoing letters to her family from Japan and Vladivostok (1911-1919) and incoming letters from family, friends, and others (1894- 1922). The Japan and Russia letters form the bulk of this section. There are approximately 450 letters that describe Rees's experiences in Japan. They relate mostly to her daily activities, replies to news from home, and housing arrangements, rather than her actual work experiences as a missionary. There are also letters regarding her work both in Siberia and on the Red Cross transport ship en route to England. The incoming letters are from her parents, Fanny H. and Henry Reese, and her siblings, Mary Addison, Harry, and Frances (1894-1918). There are also two folders of letters to Rees from friends (1904-1920), which include postcards from Japanese colleagues and students, and one folder of business letters from the missionary society of the Protestant Episcopal Church, the Bishop of Kyoto, and the Red Cross Commission to Siberia. Finally there is one folder of miscellaneous letters to and from family members in the U.S., especially between Mary, Harry, and Frances and their mother. These include some to the family from others.
The BIOGRAPHY AND MEMORABILIA series consists of a small amount of biographical clippings and memorabilia from Hartford High School, Smith College, Columbia University, Japan, and the Red Cross.
The PHOTOGRAPHS consist of a dismantled album of snapshots and postcards from Japan; twenty-six snapshots from Vladivostok of hospital personnel and patients, Russian scenes, and the transport ship; and six of Egypt which were taken on the way home from the Far East. The album was photocopied and dismantled so that the postcards with messages could be placed with the correspondence.
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Correspondence
II. Biography and Memorabilia
III. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open for research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The Sarah Tinsley Rees Papers were a gift of her niece, Sarah S. Pinney, in July 1984.
Search Terms
Rees, Sarah Tinsley, 1882-1929; World War, 1914-1918--War work--Russia--Red Cross; World War, 1914-1918--Russia--Personal narratives, American; Missionaries--Japan--History--Sources; Japan--description and travel--Sources; Vladivostok (Russia)--Description and travel--Sources; United States--History--1865-1921--Sources
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing to family
    - Japan, 1911-18 (Box 1-2, Folder 1-21)
    - Vladivostok, 1918-19 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Incoming
    - Family
      - Fanny H. Rees (mother), 1894-18 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
      - Henry Rees (father), 1892-1918 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Mary Addison Rees (sister), 1901-18 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Harry Rees (brother), 1901-18 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Frances Rees (sister), 1904-18 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Miscellaneous, 1875-1918 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Friends, 1904-28, undated (Box 4, Folder 32-33)
    - Business, 1911-22 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous, 1906-29, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- SERIES II. BIOGRAPHY AND MEMORABILIA
  - Biographical clippings, 1911, 1929, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Memorabilia
    - Hartford High School: printed material, 1919-29, [See also Oversize Materials] (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Smith College and Columbia University: records, printed material, 1901-05, [See also Oversize Materials] (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - New York Training School for Deaconesses: records, printed material, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      [See also Oversize Materials]
    - Japan: "Keepsake" book, expenditures, postcards, 1911-18 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    - Red Cross: notebooks, printed material, 1918-19 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous, 1912-19, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Japan: album contests including postcards and snapshots, 3 miscellaneous, 1911-18 (Box 5, Folder 43-45)
  - Vladivostok (Red Cross): personnel, patients, Russian scenes, transport ship (26), 1918-19 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Egypt (6), 1919 (Box 5, Folder 47)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Hartford High School: diploma, 1901 (Box 6)
  - Smith College: diploma, 1905 (Box 6)
  - New York Training School for Deaconesses: certificate, 1911 (Box 6)